you can't treat people as subhuman over
the course of decades or generations and
expect them to be cowed Martin Luther
King once said never underestimate a
man's desire to be
free and uh I think one thing that the
Israelis have always done as they've
underestimated the Palestinian desire to
be
free in the shadowy corridors of
American intelligence few names provoked
and still provoke as much heated debate
as John kiraku once a CIA
counterterrorism officer who was deeply
entrenched in the world of covert
operations across the globe John crossed
the Rubicon when he publicly denounced
the agency's use of torture this bold
move thrust him into the spotlight
earning him both lorded praise as a
whistleblower and vment condemnation as
a Trader in my conversation with John we
are not just peeling back the layers of
a man's conscious we d having head first
into the murky Waters of ethical
ambiguity National Security and the high
stakes of America's loss of moral
accountability if you watch the
following interview be prepared to
question your assumptions and to
confront the uncomfortable truth lurking
behind the whale of America's war on
terror but before we do a quick call to
action some of the best interviews on
this channel are shadowband which means
YouTube is is not presenting them to you
the fewer the latest example is my
interview with James Bamford where we
discussed the truly amazing story that
underlies Benjamin Nan's corruption
Scandal did you know that a Hollywood
billionaire not only stole nuclear
secrets from America but then sold them
to Israel and that netan helped him to
stay out of troubles to this very day
and then netan turned around and started
to ask for favors hence the private
charges in Israel against him other
examples are the interviews with the
so-called Hammer lawyer Stanley Gohan or
the interview with the former Chief of
Staff of Colin Powell who told me that
the white powder in the test tube that
Colin power showed the world when he
testified at the UN just before the war
on Iraq was actually
so so if you're interested in content
that apparently you're not supposed to
see cont content that goes against the
mainstream narrative have a look at some
of the previous interviews that we have
recorded for your pleasure and of course
it really helps to spread the news if
you like And subscribe to this channel
John kako what a pleasure having you
how's it going
in where are you it's it's I'm in uh
Arlington Virginia just a couple
kilometers from the White House doing
well thanks for having
me wow a couple of kilometers from the
from the White House what how fitting
how fitting I could I could walk
there yes John um I have you on my radar
for quite a while so I'm very happy that
this uh this conversation come to be I
have a couple of notes in front of me
and basically I do not know where to
start it's just amazing yeah I also saw
a couple of a couple I saw basically any
interviews that I could get my hands on
uh where you have spoken now uh what I
would like to focus on is the Middle
East in general and Israel Palestine in
in
particular knowing that you have
expertise on not only that area but on
that area and many and many other areas
but before we do and I know it's a
tricky one John yeah I've heard you
speaking about yourself before but in a
nutshell for viewers who do not know you
how would you how can you yeah that's a
tricky one yeah how can you describe
yourself in a nutshell yeah with all
that happened with all that you did and
how you came to be where you are
today well easy one huh to start with
yeah easy one I spent almost 15 years at
the CIA working on the Middle East
mostly on Iraq and
um and uh I spent two and a half years
as the senior investigator on the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee after that
uh working for John KY also mostly on
the Middle East but I guess I'm probably
better known for uh for exposing the
cia's torture program I blew the whistle
on the torture program in
2007 paid with it for my freedom in
2013 and um since 2015 I've been a
journalist an author columnist
commentator out there
speaking yeah you really you virtually
risk it all because there was no way of
predicting how that would end for you it
could have been 10 or 20 of whatever
years you were lucky in that sense that
it was only what was it 30 months or so
they gave you right right 30 months and
I served 23 yeah but if you seen on
other whistleblowers that's not always
the case yeah so I'm I'm very fortunate
to yeah I'm sorry to interrupt you but
in fact um I got the shortest sentence
of any of the National Security
whistleblowers and I attended the
sentencing hearings of people like
Jeffrey Sterling and uh Daniel hail and
and my name came up in sentencing where
the judge actually said I'll give you
kiraku plus 12 months or kiraku plus 30
months it was um it was awful but I'll
tell you I had very very good
attorneys um and I had a little bit of
of gy mail uh in my background we can
talk about that
and so the justice department was very
angry that um that my attorneys were
able to negotiate a short sentence and
so they sought to take out their
frustrations and anger on future
National Security
whistleblowers and if you briefly again
briefly discuss your your history in the
in the CIA yeah what are the key yeah
sure I started in January of 19 1990 uh
as an analyst on Iraq uh I served
overseas in Saudi Arabia Kuwait uh and
uh two years in
Bahrain and then went back to CIA
headquarters again working on Iraq I got
bored with that after seven years and so
I made a very unusual uh change to
counterterrorism
operations I speak both Greek and Arabic
so I went to Greece as the uh counter
terorism representative and then after
September 11th I went to Pakistan as the
uh cia's chief of counterterrorism
operations uh went back to headquarters
after leading the capture of Abu zubeda
who we believed at the time was the
number three we believed incorrectly was
the number three in
al-Qaeda and then I on the strength of
that capture I was named the executive
assistant to the cia's deputy director
for operations
and finished my career at the United
Nations yeah I wanted to flush this out
to highlight that you were not just a
minor anal analyst in the CIA you had a
serious career there right I did I did I
was very fortunate now meanwhile and I
have a list in front of you it may not
be comprehensive yeah but you're also a
prolific writer you have written about
your experience in the number of books 1
2 3 4 5 6 so The Reluctant spy right
then doing the time like a doing time
like a spy I like the title yeah yeah
the convenient terrorist yeah CIA lies
CIA whistleblower the CIA insights Guide
to the Iran crisis yeah that's a very
interesting one honorable cause so 5
six7 books right so and and you
translate your experience from the time
in in those books yeah now do when we
talk when we talk about the your career
there was of course and you mention his
name already
yeah so again in a nutshell because this
is not where I want to focus on yeah but
in a nutshell what happened what did you
do and what were achievements and very
important what you said at the time it
was believed he was number three so
explain that's the key at the time yeah
in the spring of 2002 the CIA believed
that Abu zubeda was the number three in
al-Qaeda and that he had been
instrumental in the planning for the 911
attacks none of that was true he had had
never pledged falty to AMA Bin Laden he
had never been the number three in
al-Qaeda and indeed he had never even
joined alqaeda he was a bad guy he
worked with Al-Qaeda as as a facilitator
let's say he founded
al-qaeda's uh training camps in kahar
and and Helman province in southern
Afghanistan he founded al-qaeda's safe
house called the house of Martyrs in
Pasha Pakistan he could get you false
passport reports and money and clean
phones and he could get you into
Afghanistan or out of Afghanistan but he
was never the number three we spared no
expense financially or by way of
Manpower in finding him it took us six
weeks and we found him and we captured
him now the reason that's important is
because of this belief that he was the
number three in al-Qaeda he was the
first so-called high value Target hvt
that we had captured and the first one
to undergo merciless torture at the
hands of CIA officers and
contractors yeah and I think uh Iraq was
of course a crucial moment in US history
yeah so the things that that are in my
memory are the interviews with M mlin
Albright for example where she said that
she found it Justified that we the West
starved 500,000 Iraqi children to death
yeah and then ha let me ask you a
question yeah I'm sure you know this
iconic image from Colin power testifying
at the Yan with this little glass tube
and this white powder do you know what
was in the white what was in the glass
tube yeah there was there was nothing it
it was a prop it was a prop I remember
those debates very very clearly so
imagine you have all of the um all of
the effect
analysts from the entire intelligence
community so we're talking about CIA the
defense intelligence agency Dia the
department of
energy everybody who has a stake in
trying to figure out if Iraq has weapons
of mass
destruction and the consensus was that
Iraq did not have weapons of mass
destruction the consensus was they did
at one
time and I can explain that in a moment
but there was no evidence they that they
did at that time but there was a
political decision that had been made at
the White House to invade Iraq and to
overthrow Saddam Hussein and so the the
Bush Administration was looking for
analysis to support the policy which is
exactly the opposite of what you're
supposed to do you're supposed to take
the analysis to create the policy right
you have to base the policy on the truth
they did the opposite so in the end
uh when George Tennant the CIA director
told President Bush that it was a slam
dunk his words that Iraq had weapons of
mass destruction then the decision was
made to to invade Iraq there was no
there was no intelligence analysis to
support the conclusion at all none and
so what you're talking about that famous
image of of um Colin Powell sitting at
the uh at the table the United Nations
Security Council table with John
negranti behind one shoulder and George
Tennant behind the other shoulder that
was meant to
imply that the US government was 100%
certain that Iraq had weapons of mass
destruction and the entire policy was
based on a
lie and I know that I know that it was
sold because I had Colin Po's Chief of
Staff Colonel Larry Larry Wickerson on
and he told me it was sold I I was lucky
I was sitting on the chair otherwise I
almost fell off yeah it was all fake it
was all fake incredible if you if you if
you regard the consequences yeah there
were a Million Dead Plus in the in the
intering between those first and second
golf War this 500,000 staff I mean it's
just unbelievable yeah but you said then
it then the decision was being made but
was it not so that prior years before
already America had planned to basically
um um produce a regime change or invade
seven
countries well well I I can I can give
you some background on that when I came
back from uh from
Pakistan on the strength of the appos of
beta capture I mentioned a minute ago I
was promoted to the position of
executive assistant to the cia's deputy
director for operations I went in on my
very first day and I was very
excited right I'm going to be working on
the executive floor of the CIA the
director is there the deputy directors
it's it's the the the the brain of the
CIA I was so excited and I went into the
office and I said so what do we
do and the deputy director said to me I
can't tell you anything until you go to
security and sign your secrecy
agreements so I had to go to the office
of security and they had prepared six
separate secrecy agreements for me to
sign now these were classified contracts
saying that I would never reveal what it
was that I was working on or what I
learned in that position unless the CIA
decided to declassify the
information so I went into the office of
security and I said um I said what's up
they said you have to sign these so I
signed each one of the six and when I
finished I said
okay so what's
up and the security officer said well
and he took a breath he said next
year we're going to invade Iraq we're
going to overthrow Saddam Hussein and
we're going to open the world's largest
Air Force Base in southern Iraq so that
we can move all of our air assets out of
Saudi Arabia to deprive Osama Bin Laden
of the ability to say that we are
polluting the land of the two holy
mosques I was
so taken aback by
this I stammered
out but we haven't found Bin Laden
yet thinking foolishly that that should
be our top priority six months after
911 and the security director said um
look the decision's been made and he
said the battle lines have been
drawn he said that state department
Joint Chiefs of Staff and CIA were
opposed to The Invasion but the
supporters of the invasion were the
office of the vice president the office
of the Secretary of Defense and the
National Security Council and there was
nothing we could do to stop
it later on about nine months
later the day before we crossed the
border into Iraq I was the notetaker in
a meeting a uh it's called a secure
video teleconference a cits uh that was
chaired by vice president Cheney and it
included George Tennant the CIA director
I was George's um notetaker it included
uh Secretary of State Powell uh National
Security adviser condalisa rice and um
a number of other very very senior
officials including the the four-star
general who was the commander of us
Central
Command so the vice president Begins the
meeting and says general will you give
us a briefing on the status of forces to
tell you the truth I've always been
bored by status of forces briefings I
don't understand them they're boring I
don't care he's saying elements of the
first division are here and elements of
the 15th Cavalry unit are there and
these ones are moving here and these
ones are moving there it means nothing
to
me so he's giving this
briefing and then the last thing he
says is if all go as
planned we can be in Teran by
August and very discreetly George tenant
leans forward and turns off his
microphone and he turns to
yeah I was sitting right behind his
shoulder and he turns to me and he says
did he say Tran or did he say
Baghdad and I said he said
teron and George said have these people
lost their minds and then he turned the
microphone back
on so when the meeting was over I went
back to my office and the deputy
director said how is the meeting and I
said did you know we were going to
invade Iran
and he said uh are they still talking
about that he said we're not going to
invade Iran the problem is none of these
people have any understanding of the
Middle East and none of them know
anything about Middle Eastern history
we're not going to invade Iran it's a
pipe
dream and then the next day we cross the
border into Iraq with a prediction from
the senior director at the National
Security Council that Iraqis would throw
flowers at our troops when we cross the
border and then the rest of course is
history
yeah so I mean the reasoning is
interesting yeah so we we already
established that the Americans or we the
West you know stared 500,000 children to
death and then in the second you know
the second time around they still expect
you know to be thrown with flowers yeah
incident I'm sorry interrupt there was
so much internal propaganda not just at
the CIA but in the United States that
Saddam Hussein was so evil he was the
embodiment of evil that regardless of
what the United States had done to that
country over the previous decade we
would be welcomed as liberators and that
just was not that just was not true that
was not the
reality I had just prior to talking to
you I saw an interview with General
Wesley Clark on Democracy Now where he
also uh recounts how was how he was
informed about those seven countries to
be invaded and how puzzled he was and
then he asked his he makes sure it's an
unnamed Source he can't say the name of
the person who he was talking to yeah
but he asked the person who told him
that uh why and there were not nobody
was able to give him the answer no you
know there's a famous story about um uh
Richard Pearl Richard Pearl is a famous
maybe Infamous
neoconservative he has been a lifelong
democ rat but he's he was a a a major
adviser to the George W bush white house
and there's a famous story that on
September
12th 2001 he went to see the vice
president and he said you know we have
to invade Iraq right
right and was the first one to sort of
put that that seed into the mind of Dick
Cheney there was never any evidence that
Saddam Hussein had any anything to do
with 911 and on the
contrary AMA Bin Laden hated Saddam
Hussein as much as he hated us there was
nothing Muslim about Saddam
Hussein but this was something that the
neoconservatives had planned for many
many
years the other way around was also true
you know Saddam husse hated or feared or
however you call it and he killed them
but he found them yeah that's right so
it's it's it's a mutual distaste here
that's right
yeah it would be very tempting to go
into 911 but let's not do that yeah we
said we talk about we talk about Israel
so in the context of that conversation
yeah I would be very interested to and
this is a brutal switch now yeah I know
yeah but if you talk about about Israel
and let's start with October the 7th but
before we do yeah the first I don't know
one or two months you know every
interviewer who he he his or her first
question was to the interviewee do you
condemn Hamas yeah already framing the
whole story yeah but from your
perspective with your experience in the
Middle East yeah so what's your let's CH
let's start generally yeah what's your
view on October the 7 what happened and
why well certainly October 7th did not
actually begin on October 7th it began
in you know
1948 so
just sort of as an analytic
overview you can't treat people as
subhuman you can't treat people as
subhuman over the course of decades or
generations and expect them to be cowed
Martin Luther King once said never
underestimate a man's desire to be
free and uh I think one thing that the
Israelis have always done is they've
underestimated the Palestinian desire to
be
free for so many decades we've seen
we've seen settlers just confiscating
Palestinian land burning Palestinian
Olive Orchards uh taking Palestinian
homes beating in many cases killing
Palestinians incarcerating them uh to no
end with no
reason and you get to a point where you
can't take it anymore and so
is Hamas a terrorist
organization I think probably an
argument could be made that it's a it's
a freedom fighting organization it's an
organization dedicated to the liberation
of its
people um what pushed us over the edge
finally was the election
of the hardest right-wing government in
the history of Israel I mean things have
been bad for a long time but when you
take people who have con been convicted
of Acts of
terrorism convicted of anti-arab or
anti-muslim hate crimes and you put them
in charge of
security over their
victims well what do you expect is going
to happen do you think is going to
happen now I in many cases I I blame the
United States for this because if you go
back to if you go back and look at
presidential statements or statements
made by secretaries of State between say
1948 and the early to mid
1980s you will find far more balance
than what we see today there's no
balance today if you're elected to
congress if you achieve a a ranking
position at the state department or even
at the defense department or certain at
the National Security Council you are
expected to fall into line and be 100%
pro-israel you see the same thing happen
on Capitol Hill yes or you're out you
know I remember when I first became the
the senior investigator at the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee virtually
the first call I had was from APAC the
American Israel political Affairs
committee and they said hey you don't
know us but we're APAC and
congratulations on your new job we would
like to offer you a free trip to Israel
all expenses paid and we want to give
you a tour and show you the place and I
said not in a million years thank you
very much and I declined actually
everybody declined
so you know just over the last couple of
decades we've we've gotten to this point
where any criticism of Israel and or
even worse any criticism of Benjamin
Netanyahu
as a leader or as a person is deemed to
be
anti-semitic I can't tell you how many
Jewish friends or former Jewish
colleagues I have who have been accused
of
anti-Semitism it's like are you stupid
they're Jewish they just don't agree
with the policy that you agree with this
is something we really have to very
convenient it's very
convenient and it's worse with with BDS
legislation you know many of us many
many many of us support BDS uh boycott
sanctions and investment or we support
the the the idea behind BDS but now
something like 40 States or 42 states in
the US have anti-bds laws so if I am
invited to give a speech for example
this happened to a dear friend of mine
if I'm invited to give a speech at a
university and the university accepts
state funding which they almost all do I
have to sign a
document pledging my support for for
Israel wow I'm not
Israeli I don't support Israel so why in
the world should my ability to make a
living depend on my sworn statement that
I support Israel I won't do
it so this is in the court system now
being appealed saying this is
unconstitutional I will not pledge f y
to a foreign government I won't do it
but this is how bad things have gotten
in the United States where you cannot
debate the Arab Israeli issue without
being branded an anti-semite it's
outrageous so the influence of Israel in
America I mean if you start talking
about this you're right away conspir
conspiracy theorist right the but the in
there is a very tangible and very
massive influence of the well Israel
Lobby ape you you already named it right
in the US and in the US you have like 80
no chsky told me you have about 80
million Christian fundamentalists yeah
which are actually on the side of Israel
without which no American president will
be elected so you know they need the of
this massive please yes I I I apologize
again no no no you it's your show you in
in
2008 after I blew the whistle on the
torture program I got a call from
Liberty University if if your viewers
don't know what Liberty University is it
is the largest Evangelical Christian
University in the world it is
intensely
conservative hard core right-wing
conservative bible-based
University and they asked me if I would
teach a course in intelligence studies
and I said why in the world would you
call me you and I was the same yeah I
said you and I probably disagree on 99%
of the issues we probably disagree about
what the weather is going to be like
tomorrow and without missing a beat he
said because torture is not
Christian and I said okay you know what
I'll take it and I ended up teaching
like six courses there over the course
of
years I made some friends not many I
think that they have crazy political
ideas but they're nice enough
people this idea of Evangelical support
for Israel is something that I've never
understood until one of them explained
it to
me the bottom line is they don't care
about Israel they really genuinely don't
care what they care about is the
reference in the Bible saying that Jesus
Christ will come back when all of the
Jews are returned to Israel and and so
they believe that if they support the
Israeli government and the Israeli
government's effort to U encourage Alia
or the return of
Jews then Jesus will come the end of the
world will be upon us we all go to
heaven except the bad people that will
be left behind and that's going to be
the end of it so this is this very odd
philosophy that they can force
future biblical events through
contemporary political
means it sounds insane to me but they
genuinely believe it and you're right if
if you are if you're a republican a
national candidate for for office and
happen to be a republican you need those
evangelicals to get
elected and so you're going to pledge
allegiance to Iran I'm to Israel rather
sorry and on the other hand if you're a
Democrat and most American Jews happen
to be Democrats you're going to do
exactly the same thing because it's the
Israelis represent democracy and freedom
it's the only democracy in the Middle
East people are fond of saying
incorrectly I might add and um and so
you know with the millions and millions
maybe billions of dollars that American
uh Jews pour into US
elections you know if you want to win
election or reelection you're going to
tow the
line yeah so there is a Israeli
influence right or in in America and
there's Israeli infiltration and this is
a moment this is a moment this is
something I would like to discuss with
you and have a very specific example
it's not I mean I have like four pages
in preparation of of this interview but
it's not on my on my list here
but Israel's nuclear program shrouded in
mystery up until now still not still not
officially recognized all kinds of
things yeah but and I I stumbled across
this when I started to research the the
three corruption charges against
Netanyahu one of them is particularly
interested interesting because it
involves Aaron milhan does this name
ring well no it sure doesn't
Okay I I come to a question at the end
of this year so Aon milham is one of the
most successful or the most successful
Hollywood producers ever this guy
produced Pretty Woman 10 years of slave
a Fight Club whatever yeah he is a
Israeli super spy yeah he was working
for Lam yeah um one of his operations
got got blown so the FBI knew since 20
years that this gentleman this
billionaire and arms stealer by the way
I forget I forgot to mention is an is an
Israeli spy
and the best part of it and this is
where where netan comes in
again netan was involved so milhan got a
problem in
America milhan had an interview in
Israel a Hebrew and thinking nobody in
the US understands Hebrew he thought he
can talk yeah as a result of this
interview his 10year Visa normal people
don't get a 10-year Visa but this
gentleman got a 10-e Visa got revoked he
then went to Netanyahu said B help me
Netanyahu went to Chon KY three times
it's documented three times to rein at
the Visa which eventually happened yeah
and since then netan is asking for
favors but my point of this whole story
is we know for fact from uh FBI
documents obtained through the Freedom
of Information Act that both Milan and
netan were personally involved in
stealing smuggling nuclear secrets out
of the
US this is
documented so coming back to the
infiltration of of Israel in America is
there no form I mean this is known to to
to the FBI and it must have been known
or is known to the
CIA so why is America not defending at
least itself yeah against this
infiltration that's what I mean this are
this are huge
American geostrategic interests even
yeah and they just let it go so we know
that from Carter Reagan and some other
administrations that were aware and just
kept it actually covered it up and this
only one one example um what's uncom
affair right same thing but 200 200
kilos of yellow cake dis
disappeared how can this happen does
America not even protect
itself I'm going to answer your question
with two short
anecdotes on my very first day at the
CIA uh I was in the CIA Auditorium with
all of the other new hires there were a
few hundred of us and we were given a
series of briefings by the cia's uh most
senior officials the director the deputy
director the head of security the head
of personnel people like that the head
of Counter Intelligence and the head of
security told us um that day that one of
the things that we had to be very
conscious of was Counter Intelligence
that there were countries out there that
meant to do us harm for
example there's a restaurant that's very
near CIA headquarters it's a popular
steakhouse and we were forbidden from
eating there because the KGB assumed
that we all ate there and so at any
given time the restaurant is full of KGB
officers well he said as another
example the Israeli government has two
declared Intelligence Officers in the
United States declared means they came
to us and they said these are
representatives of the intelligence
services this is the name this is where
they live this is what they're working
on one shinb bet and one
mad he said there
are9 Undeclared Israeli Intelligence
Officers active in the United States
according to the FBI spread all around
the country and they're here to steal
our defense
Secrets now why don't we do something
about that because the Israelis have
been so successful at
cultivating blind support on Capitol
Hill we don't dare do anything about it
that's why Jonathan Pard was such an
such an unusual case you know in 1985
the so-called year of the Spy Jonathan
Pard was caught red-handed working for
the mad and he was sentenced to 30 years
and he did the entire 30 years and every
time a new president came into office in
the United States the Israelis would beg
us to let him go and let him return to
Israel well it got so bad that at one
point um Bill Clinton was going to let
him go and George tenant went to see
Bill Clinton and said that if you let
Jonathan Pard go I'll resign everybody
in a leadership position at the CIA
resign and the entire leadership of the
intelligence Community will resign and
so he he didn't do it but this gives you
an example of the grasp that the
Israelis have on us I'll give you
another idea another anecdote rather a
dear friend of mine and his wife served
in Israel CIA officers and they were
declared to the Israeli uh government so
they're not doing anything the husband
was studying Arabic the uh the wife was
working with the
Israelis so
they um they go to the ambassador's
Christmas party they arrived at the 1st
of September and that December they go
to the ambassador's Christmas party and
when they came home all of their living
room furniture had been
rearranged while they were at the party
okay now that's a message the message
is we can do whatever we want whenever
we want and there's nothing you can do
to stop
us okay a few months pass they go to
another dinner party they come
home and people had defecated in all of
the toilets in their house they had
taken a [__] in all of the toilets in
the house and didn't
flush that's another insulting message
that there's nothing you can do nothing
we're watching you we can come in your
home any time we want the third time it
happened they were just getting ready to
leave uh to come back back to the United
States and the Ambassador had a going
away party for them when they got home
from that
party the dog was whimpering it was
crying somebody had cut the dog's tail
off and wrapped it in
gauze that's the relationship that we
have with the
Israelis it's very
one-sided but the political reality in
the United States is there's really
nothing you can do about
it there is a not to underestimate a
danger here I mean the Israelis bombed
the Iranian Embassy in Syria hoping to I
mean this that's I don't know how many
attempt to finally draw the us into an
attack to uh to Iran yeah yes but it's
so blatant and also so transparent not
even an an mentally incapacitated
president of the US fell for it yeah but
it's the attempt that counts right it's
the attempt that counts that's right
they tried repeatedly to draw the
Israeli to draw the Iranians into a war
and uh and the Iranians have shown great
restraint through this whole process
they just haven't taken the
bait yeah what was the story actually
um Iran
retaliated MH but very controlled they
they even informed the Americans you
know they just they did what what's the
story here what's the story they did
they they sent hundreds of drones
hundreds of
drones but the drones were slow it took
six hours between when they were
launched until they entered Israeli
airspace they informed the Americans in
advance um they informed the jordanians
that these drones would be overflying
Jordanian
territory and then the Israelis shot
down all but like seven there were
hundreds of them and there were like
seven that got
through so on the one
hand you show your public we've
retaliated on the other hand there's no
damage really and you bested the the
Israelis by not being drawn into a fight
but then on the third hand this was
really an Iranian Victory because the
Iron Dome is supposed to be Flawless and
it's not there were seven drones that
you can buy at a hobby shop or on
amazon.com that got through the vaed
Iron Dome that that was a that was an
incredible intelligence collection
lesson for the uh for the
Iranians yeah and it took it took the
American you said it already the
Americans were involved I think
uh the Saudis were involved Jordan of
course so it took multiple countries to
make sure that no bigger damage yeah
it's so Israel is not as as as
Invincible as it wants to present itself
no it's not yeah if you go back to
October 7 so out of pure interest
curiosity how as far as you can tell I
mean you're out of the agency for for
for quite a while yeah but how does this
or how did the CIA F October the 7 as
far as you can
tell I mean I'm asking for sorry I'm
asking I'm asking for one specific thing
so what what struck what struck me
immediately is the delayed response so I
have different numbers yeah but there
were between 20 and 29 on 20 to 29
different spots places the the fence was
breached yeah and in some instances it
took almost two days for the military to
arrive in a country that is so small
that that the airplane or even Apache
helicopter is in minutes there yeah and
then they shoot their own Pap but that's
a different story yeah but the delayed
response what's your view on
the way I heard it um there were
multiple organizations warning uh
netanyahu's office and the ministry of
defense that an attack was going to come
from
Gaza Egypt warned Israel twice Egypt
twice for bar yes twice you're exactly
right
twice because listen everybody's
listening to the same
Communications right you've got the
Egyptians the Americans the Saudis the
jordanians the Israelis everybody's
listening to the same cell phones and
walkie-talkies and however people are
communicating but inmar Ben gavier the
minister of National Security one of
these criminals these convicted hate
crime felons that's now in a in a
position of uh of import in
Israel thought he was smarter than
everybody else and said no there will be
an attack but it's going to come from
the West Bank and it was idar Ben gavier
that insisted that um that the that the
necessary response uh teams were
transferred to the West Bank
specifically outside of
nablo and then of course the attack came
on 29 Points up along the uh all along
the border between Israel and Gaza it's
a complete and total failure not an
intelligence failure the intelligence
was there but a a policy failure
yeah and you know another thing the the
Israeli
settlers along the line with Gaza the
Israeli settlers over the years have
been given Communications uh equipment
and they're also listening to these
these
communications Palestinian
Communications and they were reporting
back to the central government
something's happening the Palestinians
are experimenting with gliders and
balloons somebody needs to get down here
and and fix this and nothing
happened so again what do you make of
the delayed response what's your
interpretation I I really believe the
Israelis were uh asleep at the switch
they they this was a
failure plus you know I I don't mean to
get too dark but I think the Israelis
were also looking for a reason to strike
back with 1,000 times more power than
what the Palestinians used against them
on October 7th I I really believe that
the Israelis expected that nobody would
raise an eyebrow with 40 or 50 or
according to the Lance at 186,000
deaths yeah there was a I have a
document it's not mine yeah I can link
it I will link it in the in the
description of this interview there
there is a leak document from from a
from a formal um Israeli function I
don't know what it was Ministry of
something yeah not not of Defense yeah
three days after after October 7th where
they already had ready plans to R all of
Gaza of all of Palestinians and the re
they even described in which countries
to put them yeah and the reasoning was
that a a let's say expulsion of the
Palestinians would be less damaging to
Israel's Global image than to kill them
yeah I mean that that blunt and this was
three days again it's a leaked document
yeah I will I will link the I will link
it in the description from an official
Israeli I have to see Ministry of
whatever yeah so these plans they were
already made yeah and for for netan of
course for him personally October the 7
was a God sent gift given the
demonstrations that you know otherwise
he might be in prison today if there had
not been in October 7th he might be in
prison on corruption charges the longer
he can drag this war out the longer he
can remain as prime minister he's he's
arguably the most unpopular single
politician in all of Israel but he's
also the longest serving politician in
the history of Israel or the longest
serving prime minister and he knows what
trouble he's in so the longer he can
drag this out the longer he remains
free given that it's more and more
likely to say prudent that Trump will be
the next president in the US yeah if
that happens how will that affect the
situation in Gaza yeah as far as you can
tell I'm very very deeply worried about
this um there has never been a more
blindly pro-israel president than Donald
Trump blindly kneejerk uh pro-israel it
was Trump that moved the American
Embassy for example from Tel Aviv to
Jerusalem it was Trump that closed the
Palestinian office in Washington and
expelled all the Palestinian um
diplomats um excuse me it was Trump who
said during the
2016 campaign that that he could solve
the Arab Israeli conflict in a day well
he did that by screwing the
Palestinians right I mean if that's your
solution just to give the Israelis
literally everything they want and to
screw the Palestinians okay then then
there is no problem um I I fear that it
would be much much worse if Donald Trump
is elected again now listen a week ago I
would have said A week ago I actually
did say Donald Trump was going to be
president again but now Joe Biden's out
of the race KLA Harris maybe is not not
as as unpopular as we thought she was
she's going to make a vice presidential
pick that may give her a bump so I'm
optimistic that we actually have a race
on our hands now um but I think Donald
Trump is a a dangerous madman yeah
really um looking at the at the names
that are being floated for um for vice
president almost all of these names help
the Democrats
excuse me we're talking about the
without getting too far down into the
weeds kamla Harris to win the presidency
needs to win all of the solidly
Democratic states that Joe Biden won
that's easy but she needs to
win
Pennsylvania Michigan and
Wisconsin there
are swing states there are seven swing
states there are those three
Pennsylvania Michigan and Wisconsin
North Carolina
Nevada Arizona and
Georgia if she can just win Pennsylvania
Michigan and Wisconsin she would win 272
to 268 in the Electoral College and
she'll beat
him so she's considering the governor of
Pennsylvania the governor of Michigan
the governor of North Carolina she's
considering um a Bonafide American Hero
in in Senator Mark Kelly from Arizona
which is another one of the Swing States
so I think I think we really do have a
race now and another one other thing if
I could point it out
is before he was shot after he was shot
for the last six months Donald Trump has
been absolutely stuck at
46% so nothing that has happened has
bumped him over
46% Joe Biden was at
39% kamla Harris is now at
45% she'll get a bump in the polls once
she picks a vice president which will be
in the next two or three weeks so I I
think she can win it it's going to be
tough but I think she can win it
surprised I'm surprised I didn't think
so but and and again I didn't want to go
in this direction and maybe very briefly
so the assassination attempt of of
Donald Trump
right the roof was completely
unprotected how on Earth can this happen
I mean I know the the head of the Secret
Service stepped down today or yes today
yesterday today today this morning but
but how is this possible because the
roof was sloped come on I mean oh
and it was sloped like this it's barely
barely like yeah yeah right like snow
wouldn't even fall off of it it it it
was that not slope and people were
screaming here's a gun here's a gun for
two or three minutes they were trying to
yeah but but the fact that there was no
sniper on that roof no CIA sniper on
sorry no no secret service sniper on
that roof what I mean is that just
oversight or or I mean pure you
know it was a
catastrophic example of an
organization's inability to do its job
it was the worst failure in the Secret
Service since 1981 when Ronald R was
shot in the the chest uh and the stomach
um I listen I don't I don't mean to be
harsh but I I've worked with these
people for 35 years and most of them
have their heads up their asses they're
great with guns but they're just not
very
bright and over the years you get more
and more comfortable with the technology
and you feel or act like you don't
really need to do the training um 10
years ago 20 years ago this would never
have happened like did we learn no
lessons with John Kennedy did we learn
no lessons with Ronald
Reagan um that's one
thing another
thing I had a great friend at the CIA he
had spent 30 years at the Secret Service
Michael mrao he's died since but uh he
was the founder of the secret Services
Office of
Intelligence and he was fired from the
Secret Service
because as the head of intelligence he
used to review threatening letters to
the president and there was a woman in
San Francisco Sarah Jane Moore who would
write these letters all the time almost
every day I'm G to kill the president
I'm going to kill the president I'm
going to kill the president so he flew
to San Francisco and he went to her
apartment and he said Sarah Jane I keep
getting these letters you're not really
going to kill the president are you and
she said no oh I'm sorry I was angry
about the environment and I was
depressed or the president said
something on the news that made me angry
I'm not going to kill the president two
weeks later President Gerald Ford flies
to San Francisco for a campaign rally
Sarah Jane Moore is in the audience she
pulls out a 45 and she fires six shots
and tries to kill the
president that's the problem in the
Secret Service there's no followup
there's no sense of mission the Secret
Service is more likely to be in the news
for Secret Service agents getting in
trouble in Colombia for example for
going down there on an advanced trip
getting prostitutes and then refusing to
pay them and then one of them left his
badge in the hotel room and the
prostitute took
it then they are protecting the
president of the United States
and they have a massive massive budget
right which brings me to the military
huge military industrial complex so as
far as you can tell or in in in your
time and especially I mean relating this
now to Israel yeah I mean yeah the
weapons that being shipped from America
to Israel is a bonanza for those
companies who produce them right so we
talk about billions here so I mean where
are they how should I say this there are
no real incentives to to stop this right
from from that perspective no no way
listen after September 11th we
transitioned into a a a a permanent
wartime economy a permanent wartime
economy it's not an accident that there
are more millionaires in the Washington
area than anywhere else in America
including Silicon
Valley um and so if we were
to if we were to cut the defense budget
and our defense budget is so enormous
that it's more than the eight next
largest countries
combined right if we were to cut that
budget we would go into a depression in
this country an economic
depression we've we've made the
situation so dangerous for ourselves
it's like a drug addict who says well
I'm just going to smoke crack
once and then you realize wow that crack
is great I'm going to smoke it again and
again and again and again to the point
now the first thing you say in the
morning is I have to smoke crack and
that's all you can think about all day
long that's how it is with our defense
budget yeah yeah but the interest rates
of American debt is now higher than the
budget for the defense so that's right I
mean where I mean America was a I mean
that's me being black yeah and and I'm
European right I live here in the in the
safety of the Netherlands yeah but
America benefited from the last two
world wars massively especially on the
on the second world war right
now they have this depth crisis which is
actually UNH handleable yes would it not
be I mean tempting for the US and you
know we are seeing the world going
further and further further in this
funnel of violence and Global
confrontations yeah at the same time
that America gets weaker nevertheless
they still have 11 carrier carrier
groups and I think 900 military bases
around the world I mean give you have to
consider 900 you know military BAS some
of which have 50 50 60,000 people like
in in Japan okin right yes so this
massive
overblown body of arms soldiers more and
more private more and more private yeah
military IND industrial complex so is
not is not there incentive for the US in
general don't ask me who yeah to go in
that direction like like you know a a
larger
confrontation yeah
yes I think it's almost
inevitable and then you know from a
policy perspective we can't understand
how the Chinese have so many
successes right we can't understand that
when the US for example goes to Africa
and says oh let us build a base here
it'll help to protect you and the
Chinese go and say hey let us build a
highway and an airport for you it'll
help your economy develop that they
choose the Chinese we just can't
understand
that and so you're right the inevitable
outcome is is going to be War why why
prepare for war for decades with these
massive budget expenditures if you're
not going to do anything with it and so
I think we should all fear a policy
decision to go to war you know for for
example it seems to me that we are that
we have a policy of trying to provoke
the Chinese especially in this South
China Sea and we don't do it alone we do
it with the help of Japan and South
Korea and the Philippines and Australia
and even New
Zealand why what do we get out of that
other than more defense
expenditures that's a very dangerous
development if the the proxy war between
the US and Russia in Ukraine would not
be already dangerous enough right if the
situation in Gaza Israel uh Iran would
not have already enough potential to you
know no we need another bigger war with
with China that's exactly right that's
that's really I remember conversations
in um in the first decade of of the of
the 21st century uh conversations at the
White House where people would say well
of course we can fight two Wars at the
same time of course we can but no
analysis was ever made of how you fight
a twoof front War you're fighting in a
Afghanistan and you're fighting in Iraq
and then you have to worry about the
Russians and the Chinese and everybody
else at the same time it doesn't make
any
sense America will learn when the first
super carrier sinks yeah but then then
there my concern these these ships they
have nuclear not small ones even nuclear
reactors on board yeah if such a carrier
sinks and he like 2 3 4
5,000 meters time three is feets yeah
feet on the bottom of the sea with an
active nuclear
reactor I mean not even talking about
the pollution the nuclear the
radioactive pollution but this thing
could blow this could be a massive
massive I mean it's you know it's just
manl yeah awful terrible and the Chinese
have now Rockets which can destroy
carriers carriers MH yeah yes
okay
John you gave me an hour we have 1 and a
half minutes left yeah I could go on for
yeah is there is there anything that
that briefly I mean of of all your
career it's it's just incredible there
there's so many there are so many things
yeah but is there any one particular
item that you would like to would like
to mention one one question that that I
like to ask my guest is through your
career and you have you have had an
illustrious career are there one or two
situations events whatever that really
stuck out for you as a person
yeah there were several I think the most
important one was realizing that I was
not alone when I stood up for human
rights at the CIA I really believed I
was alone but the support that I got
behind the scenes was incredible the day
after I blew the whistle on the torture
program a retired deputy director of the
CIA very very important man you would
recognize his name he emailed me and he
said you've chosen a difficult path but
I'm glad somebody did I only wish I had
had the guts to do it
myself and that meant the world to me I
realized that I wasn't
alone and uh you said something at the
very start of the podcast the price has
been very
high but it was absolutely worth it
either
we're going to be this shining example
of respect for human rights and civil
rights and civil liberties or we're not
but we can't be
Hypocrites so that was the most
important lesson I
learned it's thanks to people like you
that this kind of information comes out
yeah thank you very much your dedication
with your risk I mean there must be a
I'm sure you paid a personal price in
your relationships family friends you
you you definitely learned who your who
your real friends were right and I'm
single now and yes oops is that a good
thing oh yeah you you really get to know
who your friends are yes indeed
yeah okay John on that note I I hit my
hour I went not over the time thank you
so much and we will stay in touch okay
thank you I look forward to that thanks
for having me my pleasure okay